Holocaust Collection 0008.003.004a
Jewish Historical Society of Greater Hartford
- Series II: Survivors
  - Survivors/Connecticut/Karliner, Walter and Wallerstein, Jules -- SS St. Louis, 1999; Newspaper clippings (Box 2)
    Jewish Ledger article (06/04/1999) recalling experiences of Walter Karliner and Jules Wallerstein as they mark the 60th anniversary of the their voyage on the SS St. Louis.
    Karliner, Walter; Wallerstein, Jules; Holocaust survivors; S.S. St. Louis
  - Survivors/Connecticut/Kirchheimer, Julius, 2008; Newspaper magazine clipping (Box 2)
    This folder contains a Jewish Ledger article (11/07/2008) featuring the recollections of Julius Kirchheimer concerning Kristallnacht.
    Kirchheimer, Julius; Holocaust survivors; Krystallnacht; Nazis/ Nazi Germany
  - Survivors/Connecticut/Klemens, Ruth, undated (Box 2)
  - Survivors/Connecticut/Konover, Simon, 1980; Newspaper clipping (Box 2)
    Hartford Courant article (09/28/1980) featuring the business achievements of Simon Konover, entrepreneur and CT Holocaust survivor.
    Konover, Simon; Businesses & Professions; Holocaust survivors
  - Survivors/Connecticut/Kopman, Helen, 1996/2004; Newspaper clipping and biographical info (Box 2)
    Hartford Courant article (5-28/1996) featuring story of Helen Kopman of Manchester and her perspectives on the relation of Bosnian war crimes trials to the Nuremberg Trials.
    Kopman, Helen, Warsaw, Poland; Auschwitz; Holocaust survivors; War Criminals
  - Survivors/Connecticut/Korduner. Saul, undated; Newspaper clipping - obituary (Box 2)
    Korduner, Saul; Holocaust survivors
  - Survivors/Connecticut/Korzenick, Joseph, 1980-2008; Newspaper clippings (Box 2)
    Folder contains a substantial amount of newspaper articles (1980-2008) related to the public life and Holocaust witness of Hartford resident Joseph Korzenik.
    Korzenick, Joseph; Commemorations/ Memorials; Holocaust; Holocaust survivors
  - Survivors/Connecticut/Kubran, Jack and Lea, 1983; Newspaper clipping (Box 2)
    Jewsih Ledger article (12/08/1983) featuring the story of Jack and Lea Kubran and their reunion with Antonina Wyrykowska, a Polish woman responsible for saving their lives during WWII.
    Kubran, Jack; Kubran, Lea; Holocaust survivors; Weddings
  - Survivors/Connecticut/Lazowski, Phillip and Ruth, 1997-1999; Newspaper clippings (Box 2)
    Folder contains articles from the Hartford Courant (02/11/1997, 09/20/1999) featuring stories about the lives and survivor experiences of Ruth and Rabbi Phillip Lazowski. One article details a trip Rabbi Lazowski made to Belarus to commemorate Jews massacred by Nazis during WWII. Another discusses the community service the Lazowskis participated in recounting their Holocaust experience.
    Lazowski, Phillip; Lazowski, Ruth; Commemorations/ Memorials; Holocaust survivors; Weddings
  - Survivors/Connecticut/Leifer, Mania, 1993; Newspaper magazine section (Box 2)
    Northeast magazine article (06/13/1993) featuring a story on Colchester, CT Holocaust survivor Mania Leifer.
    Leifer, Mania, Krylow, Poland; Colchester, CT; Holocaust survivors
  - Survivors/Connecticut/Lerman, Miles and Chris, 1990; Newspaper clipping (Box 2)
    Jewish Ledger article (08/08/1990) discussing Miles Lerman's invovlement with the National Holocaust Museum.
    Lerman, Chris; Lerman, Miles, Poland; Auschwitz; Commemorations/ Memorials; Holocaust survivors
  - Survivors/Connecticut/Levy, Henry, 1991; Newspaper clippings and copied biography/press release. (Box 2)
    Henry Levy, a resident of West Hartford, Connecticut was born in April 1926, in Salonica, Greece. Mr. Levy fled Salonica for Palestine in March 1942, when the town was under Nazi occupation. He was soon captured near the Turkish border, imprisoned and brutally interrogated in Belgrade, Yugoslavia, sentenced to die as a spy and shuffled from prison to prison, and, finally, deported to the Birkenau concentration camp in the spring of 1943.
    In August 1943, Mr. Levy and 3500 other Greek Jews were transported from the camp to Warsaw to remove the debris from its ghetto. They removed the corpses of Jewish resistance fighters, as well as those of the SS officers and others who fought against the resistance. They also built what became the Warsaw concentra¬tion camp, and witnessed such horrors as the degrading conversion of a synagogue into a stable for SS horses. In November 1944, the Warsaw Ghetto was razed and its inhabitants moved to the Dachau concentration camp. More than half perished during the long journey on foot. At the camp, Mr. Levy was assigned to help in the manufacture of concrete blocks and ammunition. He made sure that much of his output was defective. On March 27, 1945, Dachau was evacuated and its inhabitants transported by train, for 33 days, without apparent destination. On May 1, 1945, the train doors opened and the captives were free. The war was over.
    Newspaper articles from the Hartford Courant (09/17/1991) featuring story on West Hartford Holocaust survivor Henry Levy.
    Levy, Henry, b. 1926, Salonica, Greece; Holocaust survivors; West Hartford, CT
  - Survivors/Connecticut/Libitsky, Eva and Martin, 1990; Newspaper clipping (Box 2)
    Jewish Ledger article (10/04/1990) featuring story of Eva and Martin Libitzky of Manchester traveling to Poland to visit Holocaust sites.
    Libitsky, Eva; Libitsky, Martin; Holocaust survivors; Manchester, CT
  - Survivors/Connecticut/Lindauer, Walter, 1989; Newspaper clipping (Box 2)
    West Hartford News article (09/07/1989) featuring a story on the visit of Walter Lindauer to Stuttgart, Germany.
    Lindauer, Walter, b. 1914, Buttenhausen, Germany; Holocaust survivors; Jewish War Veterans
  - Survivors/Connecticut/Lubka, Sam, 1990; Newspaper clipping (Box 2)
    Calfas Hatters. (Hartford, CT -- est. 1902); Lubka, Sam; Businesses & Professions; Holocaust survivors
  - Survivors/Connecticut/Luftglas, Roman, 1988/1996; Newspaper clippings (Box 2)
    Roman Luftglas was born in 1925 in Poland. A Holocaust survivor, Roman later worked in Germany at the American Joint Distribution Committee and showed movies to fellow survivors at DP camps. An American man named Dr. Haber gave Roman the opportunity he had been unable to fulfill: going to America. On a trip to Munich to clean his camera equipment, Mr. Luftglas learned that Dr. Haber had found a sponsor for him, the Jewish Committee of Columbia, SC, to come and live in the United States. Before leaving for the U.S., Roman spent time mastering trade skills such as welding and auto-mechanics in attempts to learn a skill that may be useful when he arrived in the States. Three months later on a Saturday in 1950, Roman arrived by ship to Columbia, South Carolina. Roman began to work immediately and held a series of jobs that required his technical and mechanical skills. After applying for citizenship, Roman was drafted into the United States Army at the age of 25 and was sent to Fort Jackson, South Carolina to begin basic training. Roman was then sent to Louisiana and was trained to be a CW operator which he mastered, though it was very difficult. Part of the 45th Infantry, also named Thunderbird, Roman was shipped out to Japan and two weeks later arrived in Korea to replace the 40th Division that had been wiped out. Roman spent many hours in a watch tower looking over both sides of the war and took action when necessary. The time that Roman spent in the Korean War was well served and he took many steps to insure his security and survival during the war. He used his skills that he already acquired to better serve his fellow soldiers and himself. He cut hair and showed movies in order to stay safe from patrol duty in the mountains of Korea. He was sent back to the United States and released from the Army at age 27, and moved to Hartford, CT where he met his wife, Goldie. Roman opened a camera shop in West Hartford that he has owned for 40 years. Recently, the Holocaust Museum in Washington, D.C. has donated $10,000 in Roman's name for all that he has accomplished. Throughout his experiences he learned how to be an American by interacting with other soldiers and greatly values what he learned in the Army today. Roman learned to do everything to the best of his ability in order to be proud of himself and his accomplishments. He used the skills he had mastered to create a life that he is very proud of.
    This folder contains a biographical sketch and newspaper articles related to Luftglas' camera business.
    Luftglas, Roman; Businesses & Professions; Holocaust survivors
  - Survivors/Connecticut/Melcher, Helene, 1965; Photocopy from holiday publication (Box 2)
    Folder contains copy from memoir recollections written by Helene Melcher entitled, "A Bridge of Light Across the Darkness".
    Melcher, Helene; Holocaust survivors
  - Survivors/Connecticut/Meriden, David, 1981-1983; Newspaper clippings (Box 2)
    Jewish Ledger articles (06/18/1981, 06/09/1983) featuring stories about West Hartford resident and Holocaust survivor, David Merin.
    Merin, David, Poland; Holocaust survivors
  - Survivors/Connecticut/Merin, Leonard, 1987/1995; Newspaper clipping (Box 2)
    Hartford Courant 10/23/1995 obituary of Leonard Merin. Additionally, a Jewish Ledger article (8/13/1987) featuring David Merin's and Helen Kopman's recollections of the World Gathering of Holocaust Survivors in Jerusalem.
    Kopman, Helen, Warsaw, Poland; Merin Brothers, Inc.. (Hartford, CT); Merin, Leonard, Poland; Holocaust survivors
  - Survivors/Connecticut/Nachtigal, Samuel, 2008; Newspaper clipping (Box 2)
    Jewish Ledger article (07/04/2008) featuring story related to Samuel Nachtigal and Holocaust compensation.
    Nachtigal, Samuel; Holocaust survivors
  - Survivors/Connecticut/Ostfeld, Bernard, 1978-1990; Newspaper clippings, manuscripts, transcription records (Box 2)
    Folder contains several newspaper articles featuring stories on the Holocaust experience of Bernard Ostfeld. Also included are written manuscripts, and an oral history transcription.
    Ostfeld, Bernard; Catholic Church; Holocaust; Holocaust survivors; Oral History
  - Survivors/Connecticut/Patron, Rachel, 1981; Newspaper clipping (Box 2)
    Hartford Courant newspaper article (03/12/1981) written by Rachel Patron recalling childhood memories.
    Patron, Rachel, Writer, Poet; Bloomfield, CT; Holocaust survivors
  - Survivors/Connecticut/Post, Florence, undated (Box 2)
    Post, Florence, Homemaker, b. 3/4/1936, Kovna, Lithuania; Holocaust survivors
  - Survivors/Connecticut/Ressler, Molly, 1978; Newspaper clippings (Box 2)
    Jewish Ledger article (07/27/1978) featuring story of Molly Ressler's escape from Nazi Europe.
    Ressler, Molly; Holocaust survivors; West Hartford, CT
  - Survivors/Connecticut/Rothenberg, Lottie, 1987/1993; Newspaper clippings (Box 2)
    Folder contains Hartford Courant (05/14/1987) and Jewish Ledger (07/23/1993) articles written by Lottie Rothenberg recalling shtetl life and liberation.
    Rothenberg, Lottie; Holocaust survivors; Shtetl life
  - Survivors/Connecticut/Rubel, Lore and Neuhaus, Rose, 1980; Newspaper clipping (Box 2)
    Jewish Ledger article (12/11/1980) featuring story of how Lore Rubel and Rose Neuhaus were assisted in escape by a Dutch family during WWII.
    Neuhaus, Rose; Rubel, Lore; Holocaust survivors
  - Survivors/Connecticut/Scheer, Bernard, 1989; Newspaper clipping (Box 2)
    Hartford Courant article (09/1989) releasing information concerning Bernard Scheer's publication "Don't Cry Out Loud".
    Scheer, Bernard, Author, Dental Technician, b. 1926, Podhajce, Poland; Holocaust survivors
  - Survivors/Connecticut/Schiller, Martin, 2009; Newspaper clipping (Box 2)
    Hartford Courant article (05/10/2009) featuring the community service of Holocaust survivor and author Martin Schiller of Fairfield, CT. Schiller speaks at Newington High School.
    Schiller, Martin, Author, Engineer, Tarnobrzeg, Poland; Holocaust survivors
  - Survivors/Connecticut/Schindelman, Sylvia, 1992; Newspaper clipping (Box 2)
    Hartford Courant article (06/20/1992) featuring the Sylvia Schindelman's participation in organization reuniting Holocaust survivors.
    Holocaust Child Survivors of Connecticut. (Wilton, CT -- 1991); Schindelman, Sylvia; Holocaust survivors
  - Survivors/Connecticut/Schwartz, Bernard, 1998/1999; Newspaper clippings (Box 2)
    Folder contains Hartford Courant article (04/23/1998) featuring recollections of Holocaust experience by Bernard Schwartz and David Lipstadt. Also Jewish Ledger article (06/05/1999) discussing Schwartz's participation in Vad Vashem award.
    Lipstadt, David; Schwartz, Bernard; Holocaust survivors
  - Survivors/Connecticut/Schwartz, Lori, 1985; Newspaper clippings (Box 2)
    Hartford Courant article (06/08/1985) featuring Holocaust survivor and Avon resident, Lori Schwartz's participation in the University of Hartford Terezin exhibit, 1985.
    Schwartz, Lori; Holocaust survivors; Nazi concentration camps
  - Survivors/Connecticut/Second Generation/Charov, Helen, article about her mother Tatayana Artemyeff, 2001; Newspaper; Charov, Helen, Author (Box 2)
    Northeast Magazine cover feature (09/06/2001) on the the memoirs of Helen Charov and her mother Tatyana Artemyeff.
    Artemyeff, Tatyana; Holocaust -- Second Generation; Holocaust survivors
  - Survivors/Connecticut/Second Generation/General, 1990-2000; Newspaper clippings (Box 2)
    Folder contains serveral miscellaneous newspaper articles relating stories of survivors and their children's experience.
  - Survivors/Connecticut/Second Generation/Kassow, Samuel, 1999; Newspaper clipping
    Jewish Ledger article (09/24/1999) featuring Sam Kassow's recollection of how his mother was saved during WWII.
    Kassow, Samuel, Professor; Holocaust -- Second Generation; Holocaust survivors
  - Survivors/Connecticut/Second Generation/Ross, Libby Antarsh, 1996; Manuscript and letter; Ross, Libby Antarsh (Box 2)
    Memoir account of Libby Antarsh Ross's visit to Male Siedlische, Poland.
  - Survivors/Connecticut/Shainfarber, George, 1999; Newspaper clippings (Box 2)
    Hartford Courant article (01/24/1999) featuring the stories of Holocaust survivors including George Shainfarber, Fred and Regina Jacobs, and Roman Luftglas.
    George Shainfarber was born in Lodz, Poland, where he lived with his parents and younger sister. In 1939, during the German occupation, his family was forced to move to the Lodz Ghetto.
    He attended gymnasium (secondary school) there for one year after which he was ordered to work in a factory. In 1944 his family was sent to Auschwitz when the ghetto was liquidated. From Auschwitz, Mr. Shainfarber was sent to the concentration camp Friedland In Germany. After liberation in May, 1945, he was reunited with his father, but his mother and sister had perished. In 1948, he graduated from the ORT Technical School in Germany and immigrated to the United States in 1950. He completed his education and worked in large appliance sales for many years. As of 1999, Mr. Shainfarber is an active member of the Hartford Jewish Historical Society, the Holocaust Commemoration Committee, and lectures about the Holocaust at schools and colleges. He is married, has two married daughters and six grandchildren.
    Jacobs, Fred; Jacobs, Regina; Luftglas, Roman; Shainfarber, George; Holocaust; Holocaust survivors
  - Survivors/Connecticut/Sheiman, Ilse, 1985-1989; photocopies and newspaper clippings (Box 2)
    Folder contains a memorial poem written by Ms. Sheiman dedicated to her husband John Sheiman. Also included is a copy of a letter from Elie Wiesel regarding this poem and a letter from Congresswoman Barbara Kennelly replying to Ms. Sheiman regarding Pres. Ronald Reagan's trip to Bitburg Cemetery in Germany.
    Sheiman, Ilse; Wiesel, Elie, Author, Doctor; Holocaust; Holocaust survivors; Poetry
  - Survivors/Connecticut/Shenkman, Herbert, 1981; Newspaper clipping (Box 2)
    Newspaper article (01/08/1981) featuring Herbert Shenkman's slide presentation at Ararat Lodge breakfast meeting in 1981.
    Shenkman, Herbert; Ararat Lodge; Holocaust survivors
  - Survivors/Connecticut/Silberman, Leo L., 1987; Newspaper clippings (Box 2)
    Jewish Ledger article (12/17/1987) featuring the story of Leo L. Silberman of Bloomfield as he prepared to testify against an ex-Nazi camp commandant.
    Silberman, Leo L., Physician; Bloomfield, CT; Holocaust survivors; Living in a Ghetto
  - Survivors/Connecticut/Silverton, Leo, 1989; Newspaper clippings (Box 2)
    Bloomfield Journal article (09/01/1989) featuring the story of Leo Silverton and his family as he was to embark on a family reunion trip to Germany.
    Silverton, Leo; Bloomfield, CT; Holocaust survivors
  - Survivors/Connecticut/Sluis, Henry, 2002; Newspaper clipping (Box 2)
    This folder contains a Hartford Courant obituary article (11/17/2002) concerning the life of Henri Sluis, musician, realestate investor, and Holocaust survivor.
    Sluis, Henry, Real Estate Investor, Musician, Antwerp, Belguim; Holocaust survivors
  - Survivors/Connecticut/Soumerai, Eve, 1988-1992; Newspaper clippings (Box 2)
    This folder contains a series of newspaper articles both featuring Eve Soumerai as a subject, and some written by Ms. Soumerai. Also included is Ms. Soumerai's resume and materials related to her consulting and teaching at Hebrew College.
    Soumerai, Eve; Commemorations/ Memorials; Holocaust; Holocaust -- Second Generation; Holocaust survivors
  - Survivors/Connecticut/Springer, Irene, 1985; Newspaper clippings (Box 2)
    Jewish Ledger article featuring the story of Irene Springer and her recollections of her concentration camp experience.
    Springer, Irene; Auschwitz; Hebrew Home and Hospital; Holocaust survivors; Nazi concentration camps
  - Survivors/Connecticut/Sprung. Ita, 1988; Typed letter (original); Katz, Harriette (Box 2)
    Folder contains letter written by Harriette Katz to Marsha Lotstein regarding the story of Holocaust survivor Ita Sprung.
    Separated Materials note
    Sept* 5, 1988
    Marsha,
    There is a Jewish widow (refugee from Poland) in West Hartford, 1179 Boulevard Mrs. Ita Sprung, whose story during the Holocaust should be taped by you. She is very emotional, she cries when she tells her story, so don't tape her story in front of an audience.
    Her story is very unusual for several reasons (I think) maybe I'm wrong, because she posed as a shiksah, wore a cross on a chain and was harbored by nuns in a convent.
    Her first husband was taken from her; her sister was cremated, her parents too, etc. But there is another aspect to her story (the same as the one I heard from a refugee from Austria) which I wonder if it has been documented* Are others aware of this gruesome aspect2 It is the resentment of certain Jews against other Jews. Am I the only one who hears this?
    The one from Austria warned me (wishful thinking) that we Jews in America will experience some day what the Jews in Austria, Germany, Czech., Poland et al have all experienced. This resentment was triggered by the fact that she could not get visas for her son, his wife and their son to come to the U.S. I helped her write letters to Congressmen and Senators and others on a Mag Card machine at work. She had to join them in Israel and she didn't want to go there. She loved the U.S. with its Social Security. She was a furrier and was doing very well here financially. But she writes to me from Haifa and has adjusted very nicely in Israel. She said we are too smug*
    The one from Poland is very bitter toward us Americans because she said we didnTt heIn buy up land in Palestine before Hitler and that's why the Jews were not able to escape from Poland, Germany, and the other countries in Europe. They had no place to go.
    She is also hitter toward the refugees from Germany because she said they look down their noses at the Polish aid Russian Jews because the German Jews consider themselves to be intellectuals and superior to Polish Jews. She spoke to me in Yiddish so it is hard for me to repeat verbatim what she said. It goes something like this: The German Jews said: "Not our Hitler, he wouldn't mistreat us. He is our Feuhrer. We trust him." I think that was true of German Jews in the early 30's. Many industrial Jews contributed to Hitler's cause because they thought they were going against the Communists and they were capitalists. He pulled the wool over their eyes.
    She complained that the Jews in the U.S. didn't want to get involved in WWII. I explained that the reason we got in late is because Joseph Kennedy sent false reports to Roosevelt from the Embassy in (5'eat Britain. Joseph had 5 sons and he didn't want them to get killed in the War. He was an isolationist like Lindbergh and he was buddy- buddy with Neville Chamberlain. But Roosevelt did help Great Britain for years before our Congress declared War against Germany. I have a newspaper clipping that explains that and I worked on Lend-Lease in the Treasury in Wash. D.C. 1937 - 1942 so I know that we were helping Great Britain long before we entered WWII. Not many people are aware of this fact. We supplied Great Britain with airplanes long before Sept. 1939 when we overcame the Isolationists in the U.S. and entered WWII.
    I wonder if the historians of the Holocaust are aware of the resentment of Jews against Jews. It amazes me. I am shocked by it and can hardly believe it but I heard it with my own ears. They don't have much respect or gratitude toward us American- Jews. I resent that. Call me and tell me what you think of this subject.
    Sincerely, *and think it will never happen to us. She was very bitter toward us. Harriette Katz
    Lotstein, Marsha; Sprung, Ita, Poland; Anti-Semitism; Holocaust survivors
  - Survivors/Connecticut/Sprung, Leon, 1980; Newspaper clipping (Box 2)
    Jewish Ledger article (08/21/1980) featuring the story of Leon Sprung, Holocaust survivor, and his reunion with Karol Kassian, the man who saved Sprung's life during WWII.
    Sprung, Leon; Holocaust survivors
  - Survivors/Connecticut/Stargardter, Hans, 1997; Manuscript (copy); Stargardter, Hans (Box 2)
    This folder contains a copy of memoirs entitled 'My Experiences of Hitler's Germany' written by Hans Stargardter, 1997.
    Holocaust survivors; pre-Nazi Germany
  - Survivors/Connecticut/Strauss, Herbert and Lotte, 1982; Newspaper clippings (Box 2)
    Jewish Ledger article (04/22/1982) featuring story of Herbert and Lotte Strauss and their appearance on CPTV.
    Strauss, Herbert; Strauss, Lotte; Holocaust survivors
  - Survivors/Connecticut/Vogel, Jack, 1989; Newspaper clipping (Box 2)
    Jewish Ledger article (07/20/1989) featuring the story of Jack Vogel, Bloomfield, CT Holocaust survivor, and his return to Lvov, Poland (now part of Soviet Union).
    Vogel, Jack; Bloomfield, CT; Holocaust survivors; Nazi concentration camps
  - Survivors/Connecticut/Weilheimer, Richard, 2005; Book; Weilheimer, Richard (Box 2)
    Folder contains a signed copy of Weilheimer's book entitled "Be Happy, Be Free, Dance!: A Holocaust Survivor's Message to His Grandchildren".
  - Survivors/Connecticut/Weis, Magda, 1983; Photocopied newspaper clippings (Box 2)
    Folder contains West Hartford News article (04/07/1983) featuring the Auschwitz survivor story of Magda Weis.
    Weis, Magda; Auschwitz; Holocaust survivors
  - Survivors/Connecticut/JHSGH Oral History Project, 1979; Newspaper clippings (Box 2)
    Fishman, Bob; Freedman, Roger; Jacobs, Fred; Neiditz, Daniel; Vlock, Laurel; Holocaust survivors; Jewish Historical Society of Greater Hartford; Oral History
  - Survivors/ Klein, Gerda Weissmann, 1994; Newspaper clippings (Box 2)
    Jewish Ledger articles (05/06/1994, 04/071995) discussing Gerda Klein's participation in local Hartford events.